[Bright music]
>>One million neural
connections per second.
That's the speed at
which brain science
clocks a child's brain
developing between
birth and age three.
And science shows
that early nurturing from
parents and caregivers
is vital to boosting
those neural connections
and budding brains
and to equipping babies
with the sensory pathways
and brainy bedrock
they'll need to succeed in life.
Yet, while every child needs
early parental involvement,
for kids with learning
and attention issues,
early intervention
stands as perhaps
the most consequential
thing parents can do
to ensure their child
reaches their full potential.
Early intervention primarily
describes services and support
children from birth to age 3
with learning and
attention issues received
that address their
individual communication,
social, emotional,
and learning needs,
helps them to reach their peak,
and can reduce the likelihood
the child will experience
more serious mental health
problems down the line.
On this episode, we
visit a Texas school
for neurodivergent students
that finds fun ways to
tackle the serious task
of early intervention.
Next, our panel of
national experts
discusses how early intervention
can enhance children's outcomes.
Later, you'll meet our
latest difference maker,
a renowned British academic
with much to say about
equity in higher education
who through childhood,
negotiated silence in autism.
First, we traveled to
the Joy School in Houston
where we learned that sometimes
the answers to early
intervention with the three Rs
means getting your
hands dirty, literally.
Chief correspondent Cindy
Peterson brings us the story.
>>It isn't unusual
for parents to burst
into the bathroom
and find their little ones
playing with dad's shaving cream
for a bit of mischievous fun.
But at the Joy School
in Houston, Texas,
elementary students are
lathering up the Barbasol
for a greater purpose.
>>Reading is a rope and there
are lots of different layers
and things that the
kids need to learn.
And so, focusing on those
early foundational skills
like the phonics, the
phonemic awareness piece,
and then getting them
to blend and decode
and encode to that spelling.
And then, but also we do talk
a lot about the comprehension.
So, reading books,
doing a think aloud.
So, if I read a story,
retelling the story,
talking about what I think the
characters might be feeling,
and then having the kids
share their thinking,
really lays again,
a solid foundation
for them as they get older.
>>This is just one
of the tools in the toolbox
that teachers at this
private school for children
with learning and
attention differences
help support and
equip their students
through early intervention.
>>One of the biggest
things that we do
is we teach explicitly.
And so,
we're not just assuming
that a child is going to
learn to read by osmosis,
we know that they
need systematic,
detailed instruction,
explicit instruction
in how to read
and what the rules
are for reading.
And that makes all the
difference in the world.
>>Early
intervention programs
are designed to enhance
the learning abilities
and functional
skills of these kids,
boosting their self-esteem
and improving communication,
social interaction,
self-regulation,
problem solving,
and other critical skills
necessary for success.
>>One of the
commonalities is that
these are the kiddos
who don't necessarily
pick up on things intuitively.
So, what might come
naturally to other kids
has to be more directly
taught with our kids.
So, the earlier we can
teach them how to learn,
how their brain works,
how to know if they're
paying attention,
how to know if they are on task,
how to know when
they do need help,
and how to specifically hone
in on where they need help,
the more beneficial that's
going to be in the long run.
>>There's some
statistics that say,
if you don't provide
intervention
before the age of eight,
they're likely to struggle with
reading through high school
like, it's a 75% chance.
So, when you can
help remediate those,
specifically in the phonological
component of the brain
when you can remediate
and teach them in kindergarten,
then their likelihood of not
having significant struggles
throughout is much higher.
>>Oftentimes, a low
self-esteem or self-image
clouds a child's mind
when they struggle
with basic learning.
That's why the Joy School
aims to not only provide
strategies for success,
but promote an
environment of positivity,
celebrating each child's
individual growth.
>>The longer kids
struggle in school,
whether that's
academically or socially,
the more their
self-esteem is impacted
and that's what
takes longer to fix.
There are all kinds of
scientifically backed
methods for teaching
reading or teaching math
for kids who struggle
in those areas,
but reclaiming a
child's self-worth
and helping them realize
that they are capable,
despite whatever learning
differences they may have,
that takes a lot longer.
>>Adults like to say
that kids are resilient
but they're also very observant
and they're often big feelers
and school is like
their occupation.
And so, when they feel like
they're not good at it,
the impact that it can have
on how they feel as
a person can be huge.
>>As a transitional program,
the Joy School has
seen great success
in acclimating kids back into
public or private schools
after equipping them with the
tools they need to succeed.
>>On average, our kids are
here three to four years
and so, we've shown repeatedly
that this little
detour where we can,
you know, give kids
some breathing room
and take a detour off
the standardized path
of what they're supposed
to be able to do
just because they're
in X grade level
is really, really effective.
>>Max, who had no
self-confidence,
didn't wanna leave the house,
didn't wanna go on play dates,
didn't want to try new things,
stuck to himself
to now outgoing, willing
to do new things,
willing to try different things
that are outside of
his comfort zone,
and then excited,
more importantly.
Just the overall excitement
about coming to school
and sharing his
experiences at school
and showing what he's learning,
showing that he can do
the math that he can read.
Where before everything
was a struggle.
>>More than anything
with both of my kids,
the skills that they
were taught here,
they know how to
advocate for themselves.
They appreciate who they are,
they have a ton of
self-confidence,
and I think that that gift
that they both learned
at an early age
is gonna serve them
well, not only in school,
but I think it's gonna serve
them throughout their careers.
>>For A World of
Difference, I'm Cindy Peterson.
>>Next, our expert panel
takes a closer look
at early intervention
and offers a game plan
for parents to follow.
Dr. Oksana Hagerty
is an educational
and developmental psychologist
who serves as a
learning specialist
and the dean of the
Center for Student Success
at Beacon College in
Leesburg, Florida,
the nation's first accredited
college or university
dedicated to educating
neurodiverse students
with learning disabilities,
ADHD, dyslexia,
and other learning differences.
Hagerty specializes
in academic support,
cognitive abilities, learning
disability interventions,
and educational and
developmental psychology.
Dr. Emily Knight, MD and PhD
is an assistant professor
of developmental behavioral
pediatrics and neuroscience
at the University of
Rochester Medical Center
in Rochester, New York.
Dr. Knight's clinical focus
is providing patient-centered
subspecialty care
for children and adolescents
with a wide range
of neurodevelopmental
disabilities.
She also conducts research
that aims to understand
neuro mechanisms
of sensory perception
in individuals on
the autism spectrum.
Dr. Kimberly Mosca
is head of school
at Tribeca Preparatory School,
a 12 month independent special
education early childhood
and elementary
school in New York
that prepares their students
for a less restrictive
environment
by developing their
academic and social skills.
Mosca is a licensed
behavior analyst,
a board certified
behavior analyst doctoral,
and a certified
special education
and general education teacher.
And we're gonna start our
conversation with Dr. Hagerty.
What is early intervention
and how can it benefit
neurodivergent children?
>>In this strictest
sense of this word,
early interventions are
support and services
that are provided to children
under the age of three
and this can be speech
therapy or physical therapy
or any other supports
that are needed
to the children and families
with neurodevelopmental
disabilities.
However, and I work for college
and it may be a very
interesting combination
that I'm here to talk
about early interventions
but I wanted to expand
the knowledge of,
the concept of early
interventions to just say that
early intervention would
be any intervention
that is done during the critical
or sensitive period of time.
Because when we talk about,
for example, college students,
we do see that those students
who didn't have
reading interventions
during their first or second
grade in elementary school
are lagging behind.
So, to me, if we're talking
about the stricter sense
of the word early interventions
or interventions done
before the age of three.
In the broadest
sense of this word,
these are any
interventions that are done
during sensitive or
critical periods of time
of the development
and it can be
reading interventions
or social skills interventions,
can be any interventions done
between the birth of the child
to the probably
late adolescence,
if we're talking about
executive functions.
>>Thank you, Dr. Hagerty.
So, Dr. Knight, what is
the most recent research
showing about the efficacy
of early intervention
for neuro divergent students?
>>Yeah, so we know from research
that early childhood is a period
where the brain is growing
and has really enormous
capacity for change.
And so, what we have is
a wonderful opportunity
to support that brain
development
with early interventions.
And what our research
is showing is that
targeted early interventions
are associated with improvements
in some really key areas
for neurodivergent children.
For example, we may
see improvements in
language, play, joint attention,
and daily living function.
And as Dr. Hagerty referenced,
even beyond the
child themselves,
early intervention
plays an important role
in helping support the
whole family and parents.
And so, when families are
connected to interventions
and feel empowered to
advocate for services,
they report that
they feel less stress
and they feel better equipped
to support their
child's development.
>>Thank you.
So, Dr. Mosca,
what are some of the
learning and attention issues
that these neurodivergent
children are facing
that would require
early intervention?
>>That's a really
great question.
A lot of the early
signs are things
that we might not
really think of.
So, a lot of times there are,
you know, in the
past couple years,
there's been things
you might think of,
lack of eye contact
or maybe repetitive movements
such as hand flapping.
But there's really three
areas that are very common
in developmental
delays that signal us
that a child likely
needs some intervention.
So, the first area is in
the area of communication.
So, that can really span
from receptive language
of not being able to
respond to one's name
to even further
on in development
in the lack of ability
to read social cues
and be able to change topics.
So, some of our families
have a hard time
thinking that there is
a communication issue
because they'll say,
well, Billy can speak
about dinosaurs for hours
but that is an issue in
pragmatic language development.
And some of these children
actually are speaking
before the age of three.
And that is an area
that is very difficult
for families to often identify
because they might actually
have a pretty robust vocabulary.
The children that have a
little bit more obvious signs
of not being able to
respond to their name,
follow directions, or say
their wants and needs,
those are signs that
parents typically see
a little bit earlier.
Another area is with
frustration tolerance.
So, children tend to
have a harder time
soothing themselves.
And parents notice that the
tantrums might last longer
if the child doesn't
get something
just the way they want it.
And oftentimes it seems kind
of like, a strange reason.
So, it might be,
parents are asking themselves
I just don't understand,
why is my child upset?
With that being said, they
might also have difficulties
being soothed by themselves,
so self soothing
or by a caretaker.
So, a lot of times as
parents were taught,
you know, to rub
the back or a coup
or do things to make
them or children calm.
But a lot of times
these children
aren't able to calm themselves
with those typical kind of
ways of calming a child.
And the last area,
which is really
is a sign that
children do need help
is the delayed acquisition
of daily living skills.
So, that can include toileting,
brushing, teeth,
eating, dressing.
So, these skills
are typically skills
that children learn
through imitation,
imitating their caretakers.
At a certain age you hear
that a child wants to do
something on their own.
So, a lot of times our children
might have delays in those areas
and those skills have to
be directly taught to them
and then repeated.
So, those would be, I would say
the three big areas that
family should be looking at.
>>Thank you.
So, Dr. Hagerty, can you
give us some examples then
how early intervention
can help to
mitigate and remediate
some of these issues
that children who are neuro
divergent might experience
during this particular
developmental time?
>>In these recent years
and since we are
college specializing
on working with students with
learning intentional issues,
there has been research that
supports the point of view
that specific learning
disabilities can develop
in response to an
extreme lack of
environmental
stimulation early on.
So, any kind of deprivation
early on will eventually lead,
will eventually lead to a
specific learning disability
or may lead to a specific
learning disability,
especially if other
factors are in place.
For example, if I were to talk
about the reading disability,
specific reading
disability, I would say that
interventions study during
the first or the second grade
are most effective.
And what they do, they
improve the efficiency
and automaticity
of reading skills
that really create the reading
experience for the students
that prepare them
later on in their life
during their teenage
or adolescent years
for reading comprehension.
Because what we are
very often seeing
students who were not
taught to read properly
during the elementary
school years,
then develop reading
comprehension difficulties,
not necessarily because
they lack fluency,
but because they lack vocabulary
or background knowledge.
And if there are no
early, and again,
I use the word
early very broadly
because when we talk about
reading comprehension
in teenager or adolescent years,
we're talking about strategies
which is executive function.
So, if there are no executive
function interventions
for students who are reading
during ninth, 10th,
11th, 12th grade,
they do not develop the
strategist that they need.
So, in this sense of the word,
we need to really know
the sensitive periods
for the development
of each ability,
in this sense, in this
case, academic ability
and provide interventions that
will create brain structures
to support the
acquisition of the skill
and the practice of the skill.
And this will create
a loner who is capable
of performing tasks
at an expert level.
>>All right. So, Dr. Knight,
can you give us a look at what
early intervention looks like
as far as helping kids
develop social skills
and be able to
develop relationships?
How does that look,
the kinds of processes
involved with that?
>>Yeah, so, social interactions
and forming relationships
are actually some of the most
complex and nuance things
that we do as humans,
even if we aren't really
thinking about it.
And so, because of that,
early in life, it is
important to establish
a strong social skill foundation
that we can continue
to build on.
And what early
intervention will do
is meet the child
where they're at
and help build from there.
These foundational
social skills.
>>Watch the full
Ask the Expert segment
on our website at AWODTV.org
if you wanna learn
more about this topic.
You can also watch or
listen on Facebook, YouTube,
or on your favorite
podcasting platform.
[Gentle music]
Next, let's reveal our
latest difference maker.
As the well worn proverb says,
"Silence is golden."
That is, unless you're
a loving mother,
desperate to hear your
child speak your name
or whisper that precious
trio of words, "I love you."
Unable to speak or write,
Jason Arday for years
bore silent witness to the world
as he navigated
his autism journey,
always observing,
thinking, and learning.
When he eventually found
his words as a tweenager,
Arday was finally free
to share with the world
the intellect that had been
percolating in silence.
In the spring of
2023, Dr. Jason Arday
became the youngest
black professor ever
appointed to the University
of Cambridge in England.
Now, the once silent
youngster speaks volumes
about democratizing
higher education
with his work as a sociologist
that seeks to illuminate the
gaps of underrepresented groups
pursuing and delivering it.
Chief correspondent
Cindy Peterson
and London based
videographer, Elijah Grant
brings us his story.
[Gentle music]
>>In a world where
barriers often obstruct
the path to success,
there are individuals
who rise above adversity,
defying expectations, and
redefining what is possible.
Meet Professor Jason Arday,
a remarkable sociologist
whose journey to success
has been nothing short
of extraordinary.
Diagnosed at an early
age with autism,
he faced significant challenges
including the inability
to speak until he was 11
and the struggle to read
and write until he was 18.
>>So, after hundreds
and thousands of hours
of speech therapy,
I was very fortunate
and I guess I look
at it as fortunate
'cause people persevere
with you, including my mom
who accompanied me to
all of those sessions
and other people.
At the age of 11, I
then said my first word,
which was, hello.
So, that was quite
a surreal moment
because as my mom
always recalls,
I used it in the right context.
What people don't
always realize is that
subsequently from
the age of 11 to 16,
there was still a
lot of learning to do
in terms of kind of phonic
exercises, soundings,
making sense of when to use
the right kind of words,
tenses and phrases in
just spoken dialogue.
It was really when
I got to like 16
that I felt more comfortable
with kind of the
English vernacular
in terms of how to use the
right types of language
and how to engage with people.
The period of kind of
living non-verbally
to be quite honest,
was a privilege.
I got to observe
and absorb the world
in a really unique way that
most people don't get to.
So, I got to observe
human interaction.
And what I became obsessed with
was how human beings
interacted with one another.
Little did I know
in the kind of
paralysis of speech
that I would be observing ways
in which I could engage with
human beings when I was older.
>>Jason then decided
to further his education
and studied to become a
teacher of physical education
at the University of Surrey.
>>I didn't, no clue what I
was doing to be quite frank.
I didn't know what I was doing.
Like, you do what you
think is your best.
You know, I didn't understand
the language people use
when they were lecturing.
I didn't understand texts.
And you gotta remember that
when I went to university,
I was 20, but I had the
reading age of a 12 year old.
And I guess a lot
of what I did was
repetition and practice,
repetition and practice.
So what I used to do was
write 500 words a day
every single day for
basically 15 years.
And I practiced and I practiced.
So, at university, this
was even more exaggerated.
I practiced and I practiced and
I practiced and I practiced.
And the thing that
kind of was the,
you know, that propelled
that way of thinking
was really my mum's
kind of endeavors
around kind of saying to me,
look, Jason, I think you
could do something great
but you're going to have to
do it in a different way.
You're going to have to do
it in an unconventional way.
>>While studying
at the university,
Jason became fixated
on higher education.
He attributes much
of his success
to the encouragement he received
from his mentor and close
friend Sandro Sandri.
>>I had a lecturer who just
got a PhD and I'd asked them,
what's a PhD?
And they said that it
means I'm a doctor now
and you just need to
concentrate on studying
'cause you won't
have one of these.
And I didn't take any I offense,
that I thought, yeah,
they were right.
I mean, why would I think that?
And so, that evening, for
some reason, I met Sandro
and I explained
Sandro what this was,
and I said to him, can
you imagine if we did one,
whatever that means?
And Sandro kind of
started laughing.
I said, what are
you laughing about?
You know, and he said,
he said, Jason, you know,
he paused after
this kind of laugh
and was straight
face and said to me,
how crazy would it be if
you managed to get a PhD?
So, at the time I was 22.
He said if you got a
PhD in eight years time,
you would've been
reading and writing
for less than 12 years.
Can you imagine if we did that?
>>Jason went on to
acquire two master degrees
and a PhD in
educational studies.
Last March, Jason became
the youngest Black
professional ever appointed
to a professorship
at the prestigious
University of Cambridge.
>>We are incredibly proud
that Dr. Arday has joined us
here in the faculty
of education.
Clearly we are very proud
because he's the
youngest ever professor
to be appointed in Oxford or
Cambridge, Black professor.
And also, because
of the contribution
that he makes here
to the faculty,
the quality of his ideas,
the quality of his research.
>>Jason's goal is
to utilize this platform
to affect real change.
He aims to open
doors for individuals
from disadvantaged backgrounds,
democratize higher education,
and lead the way toward a more
inclusive academic landscape.
>>I think there's such
a breadth of research
in the faculty of education
and I feel really fortunate
to be a small part of that.
But I feel even more fortunate
because I think
there's an opportunity
to learn some really
good practice,
you know, world leading
research and some other methods
and methodological ways of
kind of constructing knowledge
that I'm really,
really excited about.
And probably the
thing that trumps that
is just kind of seeing
hopefully the number
of Black students
that will continue to
come through these doors.
And if my appointment has
inspired that in some small way,
then that's great and I
think the privilege will be
to be able to work with them
and to be able to
harness their dreams
and to show them
everything that I know
so they can go on and be
as great as they
were destined to be.
>>For A World of
Difference, I'm Cindy Peterson.
>>Thanks Cindy and Elijah.
And congratulations Dr. Jason
Arday for making a difference.
And that does it
for this edition
of A World of Difference
embracing neurodiversity.
I'm Darryl Owens.
I'll see you back
here next time.
You can watch episodes
of A World of Difference
on the Beacon College
Facebook and YouTube channels
and on the show's
website, AWODTV.org.
The website also
provides tip sheets
and other resources for
your parenting journey.
You can watch the
show from the PBS app
available on your
favorite streaming device
and you can listen on your
favorite podcasting platform.
Thank you for watching
and supporting
A World of Difference.
[Gentle music]